<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2016-07-20T17:21:12-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Politicos' Problematic Incentives Harm Craigslist]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/politicos-problematic-incentives-harm-craigslist/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-31T23:01:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/politicos-problematic-incentives-harm-craigslist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So there&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2010/08/29/BUGI1F4F9K.DTL">even more noise</a> about suing Craigslist,
and I wish I could grab the attorneys general of 18 states by one giant pair of pinstriped lapels and shout &ldquo;You are making this problem <strong>WORSE</strong>, you buncha maroons!&rdquo;
There&rsquo;s still some space to write about this after <a href="http://stronglyemergent.com/blog/2010/the-many-forms-of-not-getting-it/">last time</a>, and I&rsquo;m gonna go ahead and fill that space.</p>

<p>The problem here is a toxic incentive structure, just like <a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/02/cya_security_1.html">the reason the TSA reduces security</a>.
The various political folk who are inveighing against Craigslist have no idea what they&rsquo;re talking about and are going to make Craigslist less useful for everyone and cost their taxpayers a lot of money in the process - and yet, for them personally, there is no downside to attacking Craigslist.
Attacking Craigslist makes them look &ldquo;tough on crime,&rdquo; look like vigorous, active advocates of the public good, and look like paragons of conventional morality.</p>

<p>The most effective things you can do to increase airline security and reduce sex trafficking are the most boring ones, and the current structure of incentives all but guarantees that those measures will not be taken, and instead countermeasures will be taken that will make the problem worse.
This underscores again the importance of narrative.
Software providers and other technical people are in danger because of these toxic incentives - people who don&rsquo;t know how your business works could have an incentive to mess with you, and are quite likely to be immune to consequences in the practical sense.
This is why we developers and sysadmins need to be aware of the social, political, and cultural context of our professional actions - the less aware we are, the more likely that we&rsquo;ll find ourselves out of a job, at the helm of a foundering company, or forced to implement asinine requirements because of forces beyond our control.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Me Or Your Lying Eyes]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/me-or-your-lying-eyes/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-19T23:01:02-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/me-or-your-lying-eyes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First there was <a href="http://thechive.com/2010/08/10/girl-quits-her-job-on-dry-erase-board-emails-entire-office-33-photos/">the big show</a>, and then <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/11/elyse-porterfield/">Toto pulled the curtain back</a> and <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/14/internet-must-be-true/">revealed the Wizard</a>.
I love the arc of this story - it&rsquo;s such a great demonstration of how much narrative matters.
The &ldquo;Jenny&rdquo; story had great, great narrative power.
It was entertaining, easy to believe, and easy to understand.
The storytellers got millions of pageviews off of it, and earned them.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, that&rsquo;s also millions of demonstrations that the weakest part of computer security is humans, not computers or anything in them.
We <em>want to believe</em>, we look for excuses to believe good narratives, and we usually find them.
Because of how we behave when someone hands us a beautiful narrative like that, the storytellers behind &ldquo;Jenny&rdquo; earned quite a bit of money - and because of the same things, scammers continue to exploit us.</p>

<p>We all need to sharpen our narrative skills, because if we just go right along with narratives that seem appealing, we will be exploited by people who can craft enjoyably fraudulent narratives.
More importantly, developers and sysadmins need narrative skills - we have to tell our users a story, and it has to be a compelling story.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The OS We're All Running]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/the-os-were-all-running/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-05T14:05:16-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/the-os-were-all-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Core Security Labs, in <a href="http://www.darkreading.com/story/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=223101626">an announcement to the press at the 2010 RSA Security conference</a>, has released a tool that makes it easier to perform attacks on users of the social network Twitter.
Recently, a subspecies of phishing attacks has arisen, called &ldquo;spearphishing,&rdquo; and it&rsquo;s this type of attack that the Core Security Labs tool facilitates.
Most phishing attacks, in which the attacker impersonates a legitimate organization and persuades the victim to give the attacker their credentials, are spammed out, sent to everyone available.
Spearphishing attacks are targeted to smaller groups, to organizations or individuals, and are often more effective because they are tailored to decieve that group specifically by including persuasive details related to the group or person.
As social networks continue to grow in popularity, the information that people share publicly on such networks enable spearphishing attacks.</p>

<p>The CSL tool specifically uses Twitter to perform spearphishing attacks.
A CSL researcher, Pedro Varangot, said that their tool is a framework that can be extended to use other social networks in the attack.
The attack tool framework is built on the open-source programming language Python, a favorite language for projects in the open-source world.
The researchers have not discovered any new software vulnerability - they&rsquo;ve just found another vector by which to deliver phishing attacks, which are basically social attacks instead of technical attacks.</p>

<p>These attacks are very relevant because they affect Windows users, Mac users, and Linux users.
Phishing attacks try to fool the user much more than they try to fool the computer.
That means that no matter what operating system you use, you&rsquo;re vulnerable to phishing attacks because you&rsquo;re still using a human brain.
Most phishing attacks, to IT people, look ludicrously simple to avoid - but there are a lot of them, and the attacker has the advantage that they only need to succeed once to win big.
We defenders need to succeed all of the time just to keep a status quo that&rsquo;s favorable to us.</p>

<p>Further, this illustrates one of Linux&rsquo;s major roles in the security world: many major security tools, especially penetration-testing tools like the CSL tool and the Metasploit framework (which some of us saw in action at the RSA conference) are built on Linux.
Linux&rsquo;s modification-friendliness means that it&rsquo;s a superior platform for performing attacks.
It&rsquo;s easier to modify Linux into an attack platform than it is to twist Windows into that role.
Regardless of platform, though, it&rsquo;s very important for us as IT people to keep in mind that we&rsquo;ve progressed in security to the point where we humans are the weakest part of the security fence - and so there are more and more attacks that target the weaknesses in human brains instead of in software.
Going forward as IT professionals, all of us will need to be educators about those weakness - and about how to compensate for them.</p>

<p>At least until we have clients and IT users who are not human, which will bring its own set of problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
