<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: leadership | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/leadership/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T21:24:43-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sherlock Holmes, Search Engine Optimizer]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-03T06:01:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A culture of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honour">honor</a> is a remarkably convenient thing for a writer.
A writer needs characters to do stupid things on a regular basis, and nothing so dependably produces idiotic behavior as a character bound by honor.
Importantly, it produces a very credible kind of idiocy:
let a character clench his hand against his chest, grit his teeth, glower, and declare that he <em>must</em> undertake some course of action for his sacred honor&mdash;
and other characters will easily nod along and agree, and readers who either live in or are passingly familiar with a culture of honor (which is nearly all of them) will understand what is going on without thinking, merely by this incident, that your character is a moron not worth reading about.</p>

<p>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle used this device frequently, and to good effect.
I recently re-read the Sherlock Holmes canon over the course of a few days, and matters of honor frequently cropped up.
I noticed, too, that Holmes, conveniently, was always on the side of honor.
There is of course a large body of Holmes scholarship, both more and <a href="http://www.tor.com/blogs/2009/02/on-the-fannish-phenomenon-of-sherlock-holmes-or-my-fandom-is-crazier-than-your-fandom">less lucid</a>, but I only propose to extend it, not to contradict it.</p>

<p>I noticed that honor, in the Sherlock Holmes canon, leads Holmes to a very effective method of search engine optimization.
The newspapers and the telegraph were impressive advances, and changed the information environment of the 19th century enormously, but personal reputation was, then as now, a tremendously important source of information about others.
Holmes consistently trades away recognition in mass media in favor of gaining personal reputation as a man of honor and discretion.
He optimizes his reputation for a specific audience:
the wealthy of England.
There are many cases that he takes on for no money at all, which serve (in addition to their stated purpose) to build a reputation for him as a man of sterling moral character.
We see his reward for this over the course of the stories:
the nobility and royalty of Europe resort to him, and reward him handsomely.</p>

<p>Holmes eschews joining the official police or intelligence forces; he is an entrepreneur.
He aims for a very specific market, and achieves his aims.
He has the dual aims of sustaining his appetite for interesting problems, and of sustaining his appetite for a roof over his head, good food, and supplies for his various studies.
This isn&rsquo;t the most obvious layer of the stories - but quickly becomes apparent on a careful reading.
Sherlock Holmes is not just a great detective, he is a very proficient marketer.
He knows where his services fetch the best price, markets there, and throws the rest to the winds.
This is only obscured by the fact that there are two prices that may be paid for Sherlock Holmes' involvement, and the more important one is that the problem be interesting.
It takes - as in &ldquo;The Adventure of the Priory School&rdquo; - quite a tremendous amount of money to awaken anything like avarice in Holmes.
Still it cannot be doubted, from the notes that his biographer gives us, that he is very efficient at making a comfortable living from himself.</p>

<p>The lesson we can draw from Sherlock Holmes is basically one about optimization.
Figure out what&rsquo;s important to you, and optimize towards that - even if it looks strange to other people.
Holmes has a way to achieve both money and a steady supply of interesting problems&mdash;
and troubles himself with nothing else, to the perennial puzzlement of Lestrade and the rest of the police forces.
Go and do likewise: build a reputation where it matters for getting what you want, and pay the rest no mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Able To Build This In A Cave]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/able-to-build-this-in-a-cave/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-06T21:00:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/able-to-build-this-in-a-cave</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I read James Tabor&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1400067677?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stronemerg-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1400067677">Blind Descent</a>, an account of cavers attempting to find the deepest place on Earth.
It&rsquo;s a flawed book, and falls to the level of being a bit forgettable, but it does contain an interesting study in leadership.</p>

<p>The book&rsquo;s central figures are the American spelunker Bill Stone and the Ukranian hydrogeologist Alexander Klimchouk.
Stone is a figure driven by urgency, and while the book examines how he has been portrayed as both a bold explorer in the mold of Hilary and a controlling, domineering expedition leader in the mold of Cortez, it&rsquo;s indisputable that he is an individualist.
He welcomes others and works well with them, but his passion for caving and exploration is deeply personal and linked to a sense of time running out.
He explores because he must.
Meanwhile, Klimchouk is convinced that only &ldquo;a big society of united people&rdquo; can reach the most profound achievements in caving.
Stone has led virtually all of the caving expeditions he has been on.
Klimchouk is content to take a role elsewhere than at the peak of the hierarchy.
Klimchouk regards the task of caving as something that demands the efforts of a community - he is a team-builder.</p>

<p>This of course oversimplifies - but it illustrates that these two leadership styles exist.
I think that for most human endeavors, we should prefer the team-building style.
Stone, in his more brusque moments, reminds me of nothing so much as a reality-TV montage.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;I&rsquo;m not here to make friends!&rdquo; attitude has become a cliché because it so strongly indicates a belief that others have nothing to offer - or worse, that working with others is a zero-sum game.
But it&rsquo;s not.
To the contrary, our friends <a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/bregman/2010/07/why-friends-matter-at-work-and.html">are our most valuable resource</a>.
In business and in other areas of our lives, we flourish in direct proportion to our ability to make friends.
This is disguised by the many different needs we have regarding friendship: I don&rsquo;t need the same types of friends that my brother does, and neither of us needs the same type of friends that our parents do.
But we all do need companionship, support, and connections.</p>

<p>In the IT world, I actually see this most clearly in Steve Jobs.
Steve Jobs seems to be almost a caricature of the urgency-driven, individualistic personality - and certainly almost all accounts portray him as an extremely demanding person.
And yet, Jobs is a team-builder.
At both Pixar and Apple, Jobs has assembled a team that reliably produces amazing things.
But it should be obvious that Jobs' individual work is not what created <em>Up</em> or the iPhone.
Jobs is not an animator, a programmer, or a hardware tinkerer.
Jobs is a visionary - and he has that crucial team-building skill of bringing together groups that can accomplish far more than the sum of individual creators' efforts.
The astonishing accomplishments of Apple and Pixar demonstrate the power that can spring from a team-building style of leadership.</p>

<p>Of course, that&rsquo;s not a huge revelation - the synergy that comes from working in teams is an advantage about as old as human society.
What we must be aware of, complementing our knowledge of that synergy, is of attempts to fake it.
The shallow, insincere corporate team-building exercise is another cliché of modern society - and that comes from attempts at control.
Complete control is a chimera.
It is unattainable, and attempts to attain it will only end in wasted resources and frustration.
So take a lesson from the cavers, and build teams that will attain your objectives.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
