<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: marketing | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/marketing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T21:38:03-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sherlock Holmes, Search Engine Optimizer]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-03T06:01:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A culture of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honour">honor</a> is a remarkably convenient thing for a writer.
A writer needs characters to do stupid things on a regular basis, and nothing so dependably produces idiotic behavior as a character bound by honor.
Importantly, it produces a very credible kind of idiocy:
let a character clench his hand against his chest, grit his teeth, glower, and declare that he <em>must</em> undertake some course of action for his sacred honor&mdash;
and other characters will easily nod along and agree, and readers who either live in or are passingly familiar with a culture of honor (which is nearly all of them) will understand what is going on without thinking, merely by this incident, that your character is a moron not worth reading about.</p>

<p>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle used this device frequently, and to good effect.
I recently re-read the Sherlock Holmes canon over the course of a few days, and matters of honor frequently cropped up.
I noticed, too, that Holmes, conveniently, was always on the side of honor.
There is of course a large body of Holmes scholarship, both more and <a href="http://www.tor.com/blogs/2009/02/on-the-fannish-phenomenon-of-sherlock-holmes-or-my-fandom-is-crazier-than-your-fandom">less lucid</a>, but I only propose to extend it, not to contradict it.</p>

<p>I noticed that honor, in the Sherlock Holmes canon, leads Holmes to a very effective method of search engine optimization.
The newspapers and the telegraph were impressive advances, and changed the information environment of the 19th century enormously, but personal reputation was, then as now, a tremendously important source of information about others.
Holmes consistently trades away recognition in mass media in favor of gaining personal reputation as a man of honor and discretion.
He optimizes his reputation for a specific audience:
the wealthy of England.
There are many cases that he takes on for no money at all, which serve (in addition to their stated purpose) to build a reputation for him as a man of sterling moral character.
We see his reward for this over the course of the stories:
the nobility and royalty of Europe resort to him, and reward him handsomely.</p>

<p>Holmes eschews joining the official police or intelligence forces; he is an entrepreneur.
He aims for a very specific market, and achieves his aims.
He has the dual aims of sustaining his appetite for interesting problems, and of sustaining his appetite for a roof over his head, good food, and supplies for his various studies.
This isn&rsquo;t the most obvious layer of the stories - but quickly becomes apparent on a careful reading.
Sherlock Holmes is not just a great detective, he is a very proficient marketer.
He knows where his services fetch the best price, markets there, and throws the rest to the winds.
This is only obscured by the fact that there are two prices that may be paid for Sherlock Holmes' involvement, and the more important one is that the problem be interesting.
It takes - as in &ldquo;The Adventure of the Priory School&rdquo; - quite a tremendous amount of money to awaken anything like avarice in Holmes.
Still it cannot be doubted, from the notes that his biographer gives us, that he is very efficient at making a comfortable living from himself.</p>

<p>The lesson we can draw from Sherlock Holmes is basically one about optimization.
Figure out what&rsquo;s important to you, and optimize towards that - even if it looks strange to other people.
Holmes has a way to achieve both money and a steady supply of interesting problems&mdash;
and troubles himself with nothing else, to the perennial puzzlement of Lestrade and the rest of the police forces.
Go and do likewise: build a reputation where it matters for getting what you want, and pay the rest no mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can Your System Account For Space Aliens?]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/can-your-system-account-for-space-aliens/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-01T07:01:34+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/can-your-system-account-for-space-aliens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jon Carroll is a friend.
Well - Jon Carroll is a friend that I have not yet been introduced to, and I am quite sure that he is willing to put me in that same category.
I read his <a href="http://www.sfgate.com/columnists/carroll/">excellent column</a> most mornings, and since we both live in the Bay Area, I am sure that we have a mutual friend-of-a-friend who could acquaint us.
I am also taking a liberty, but as a friend, and posting a big slice of one of his columns.
I am urging you to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0811803074?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stronemerg-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0811803074">buy his book</a>, because that is where I found it.</p>

<blockquote><p>I have a friend who has a friend who believes that she is a space alien.
This is not the easiest burden in life to bear.
Worrying about dental work is hard enough, being a space alien worrying about dental work can really get on a person&rsquo;s nerves.
Understand, this is a person who leads a full, active earthling life.
She holds a job, buys groceries, has relationships, drives a car, has opinions on popular movies, plays tennis, travels to Seattle to visit her sister.
She is not under the care of a physician other than her family doctor, who wants her to cut down on cholesterol.</p>

<p>But she believes that she is a space alien.</p>

<p>She doesn&rsquo;t tell many people that she is a space alien.
Space aliens quickly learn that it is a bad idea to talk about it much.
People don&rsquo;t understand.
They try to talk you out of it.
They advise you to seek professional help.
She doesn&rsquo;t want professional help.
She is entirely aware that people who think they&rsquo;re space aliens are supposed to be crazy.
It is not an honorable job classification, being a space alien.</p>

<p>So, as a thinking adult, she has been forced to ask herself: Am I crazy?</p>

<p>She has considered the matter carefully; she has talked it over with a few trusted friends.
And her conclusion: I am not crazy.
I am only a space alien.</p>

<p>Right now, she just wants to know what being a space alien is supposed to entail.
This differentiates her from many people who believe they are space aliens and are very busy following orders.
But she is not one of those people.
She does not exhibit the classic clinical symptoms.
She does not believe people are following her; she does not believe in the existence of a gigantic conspiracy designed to drive her crazy.
She does not believe that Henry Kissinger is stealing her ideas.
If anything, she wishes the Mother Ship or whatever would be a little more forthcoming about its plans.
She&rsquo;s tried listening for messages.</p>

<p>She does believe that earthlings are slowly poisoning their planet, an idea shared by many people who do not believe they are space aliens.</p>

<p>The alien chain of command is definitely nonfunctional from her point of view.
It&rsquo;s sort of like being given an office and a desk and being told that you&rsquo;re a corporate vice president, and then sitting there for years and years wondering what your job is and what the firm that employs you does.
Plus, you can&rsquo;t talk about it because people will think of you as some sort of <em>National Enquirer</em> fruitcake.</p>

<p>The more I heard about my friend&rsquo;s friend, the underemployed space alien, the more her plight sounded familiar.
We were none of us in class the day they passed out the secret of life; we all of us wander around listening for messages that never seem to arrive.
The only people who really screw up are the ones who think they&rsquo;ve gotten the message.
All those guys over the years who were convinced they had the exact date when the world would end - they&rsquo;re batting 0-for-eternity so far.</p>

<p>So here we are spinning through the unutterable void without a road map, bolstered only by the evidence of things not seen, bookended by the mysteries of birth and death, bewildered by our own emotions &hellip;
Talk about space aliens.</p></blockquote>

<p>I am not posting this to convince you that Jon Carroll is a good writer (he is) or to buy his book (you should), but to note the experience of deviancy.
The underemployed alien is experiencing deviancy in our culture&mdash;
and for all that we celebrate a certain kind of deviancy, the kind that can make money, we are remarkably intolerant of deviancy in general.
It makes me sad.
Like free speech, deviancy has benefits that outweigh its drawbacks&mdash;
I promise you that you don&rsquo;t want to live in a monoculture, and if you police deviancy, that&rsquo;s where you&rsquo;re headed.</p>

<p>Monocultures die quick, well-deserved deaths.</p>

<p>The problem is, it&rsquo;s much easier to write software that serves a monoculture instead of software that serves a real culture.
If you&rsquo;re writing something enterprisey, you can probably get away with serving a monoculture&mdash;
but if you want to serve the general public, acting like the general public is a monoculture is a deadly poison for your application.
The general public is infinitely diverse.
You, writing your very important software product, may be tempted to say - well, so what?
Eighty-twenty rule and all that.
I don&rsquo;t need to optimize that far.</p>

<p>You kind of do, though.
When you are writing for the general public, you can&rsquo;t tell who the eighty percent are, you will lose data by not considering all cases, and importantly <strong>the eighty percent will change out from under you.</strong></p>

<p>I want to say that again:
the eighty percent case, if you&rsquo;re writing software for the general public, will change out from under you&mdash;
because people and culture are either changing or dying.
You want to be able to pivot, as the startup crowd says:
to be able to gracefully acknowledge that what people want and are willing to pay for is a bit different than what you are currently offering, and to be able change modes so that you can actually deliver what people want and are willing to pay for.
By definition, you cannot know this information in advance: you must simply be able to react well to changing circumstances.</p>

<p>You are damaging your ability to pivot if you dismiss the fullness of humanity and insist that humans should change to fit your data structures.
Don&rsquo;t gratuitously handicap yourself like that.
As Paul Graham notes, you should have a keen interest in <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/say.html">what you can&rsquo;t say</a>.
Don&rsquo;t, in short, be like <a href="http://www.diaspora-news.net/2010/11/29/im-dropping-diaspora-this-site-is-now-closed/">this twerp Avery Morrow</a>, who sulks that people should fit his data structures better and that developers' convenience should take precedence, in software for a general audience, over users receiving software that serves their actual needs in their actual lives.
Morrow has it exactly backwards!
When you are a developer, <a href="http://stronglyemergent.com/blog/2010/ill-build-my-own-phone-os-with-blackjack-and-hookers/">making difficult decisions</a> <strong>is your job.</strong>
Shirking that job leads to bad software.
So I think that Morrow is a bad developer and a twerp:
it&rsquo;s clear that <em>his</em> identity has never had to deal with software that denies his existence.
If you want to know what privilege looks like, that&rsquo;s it.</p>

<p>A good developer should <a href="http://slacktivist.typepad.com/slacktivist/2010/04/empathy-and-epistemic-closure.html">have empathy</a> instead of being like Morrow.
Lacking empathy makes you stupid.
Consider this:
Morrow complains vociferously about &ldquo;gender&rdquo; being a free-form text field - and yet Metafilter, not a small site by anyone&rsquo;s lights, has had that in place for years.
<a href="http://stuff.metafilter.com/genders/genderfield.txt">Metafilter&rsquo;s gender data</a> is instructive, too.
By far the majority of users there simply don&rsquo;t give a shit about the things Morrow complains about.
They leave the field blank and go on their way.
On the other side of the scale, here we find underemployed aliens.
People have claimed as their gender &ldquo;xx,&rdquo; &ldquo;xy,&rdquo; and &ldquo;xml.&rdquo;
People have claimed &ldquo;m,&rdquo; &ldquo;f,&rdquo; and &ldquo;varies with proximity to scotland.&rdquo;
There are plenty of aliens here - and Morrow wants to throw them out.</p>

<p>Here is someone with the right idea:
Patrick McKenzie&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2010/06/17/falsehoods-programmers-believe-about-names/">&ldquo;Falsehoods Programmers Believe About Names.&rdquo;</a>
The human experience is massively diverse and, lucky you, you get to deal with it.
When you&rsquo;re a system or administrator or a developer, dealing with that diversity is an essential component of a job well done.
Especially as a developer, where your job is to make abstractions.
Abstractions and aggregations and arrays are good - but you shouldn&rsquo;t let them blind you to the fact that humans are not abstract.
The abstractions that we developers describe humans with are convenient, but <a href="http://blog.jgc.org/2010/06/your-last-name-contains-invalid.html">they&rsquo;re not free</a>.
The price is a reduced precision of representing the human experience.</p>

<p>Embrace the diversity of the human experience - especially when you&rsquo;re programming something that you want humans in general to use.
The aliens are out there, and there is no good excuse for your program to break just because they&rsquo;re aliens.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Me Or Your Lying Eyes]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/me-or-your-lying-eyes/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-20T06:01:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/me-or-your-lying-eyes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First there was <a href="http://thechive.com/2010/08/10/girl-quits-her-job-on-dry-erase-board-emails-entire-office-33-photos/">the big show</a>, and then <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/11/elyse-porterfield/">Toto pulled the curtain back</a> and <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/14/internet-must-be-true/">revealed the Wizard</a>.
I love the arc of this story - it&rsquo;s such a great demonstration of how much narrative matters.
The &ldquo;Jenny&rdquo; story had great, great narrative power.
It was entertaining, easy to believe, and easy to understand.
The storytellers got millions of pageviews off of it, and earned them.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, that&rsquo;s also millions of demonstrations that the weakest part of computer security is humans, not computers or anything in them.
We <em>want to believe</em>, we look for excuses to believe good narratives, and we usually find them.
Because of how we behave when someone hands us a beautiful narrative like that, the storytellers behind &ldquo;Jenny&rdquo; earned quite a bit of money - and because of the same things, scammers continue to exploit us.</p>

<p>We all need to sharpen our narrative skills, because if we just go right along with narratives that seem appealing, we will be exploited by people who can craft enjoyably fraudulent narratives.
More importantly, developers and sysadmins need narrative skills - we have to tell our users a story, and it has to be a compelling story.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Perception Gap]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/perception-gap/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-22T06:01:06+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/perception-gap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://stronglyemergent.com/blog/2010/you-can-learn-to-be-lucky/">my last post</a>, I touched on the perception differences between lucky people and unlucky people, comparing them to the perception differences between IT people and regular users.
The differences in thought patterns are very different, and today I&rsquo;m going to discuss that in more detail.</p>

<p>The first thing I want to discuss is the <a href="http://www.apple.com/ipad/">iPad</a>.
<a href="http://stronglyemergent.com/blog/2010/tablet-signal-tablet-noise/">Yes, again.</a>
The iPad is a great lens for talking about differences between computer professionals and non-professionals, and part of what makes it a great opportunity to talk about that is that this time, it&rsquo;s the professionals that Don&rsquo;t Get It.
Usually we&rsquo;re egotistical, prone to falling into stories about how those proles, those peasants, those <em>users</em>, don&rsquo;t get what we&rsquo;re trying to do here.
But that story completely falls apart here.</p>

<p>The iPad is about making the computer vanish.
I&rsquo;ve said for quite a while that the computer revolution has already happened - it&rsquo;s just that most of the computer that affect your life aren&rsquo;t things that you think of as a &ldquo;computer.&rdquo;
They&rsquo;re in cars, in industry, in stores, in restaurants - and in iPods.
<a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2010/02/05/how-to-compete-with-ipad">Matt Gemmell has a great piece about this.</a>
The iPad doesn&rsquo;t want to be a &ldquo;computer.&rdquo;
It wants to be a tablet.
Something that you use to get the Internet and play some games and use some apps.
It abstracts away a lot of what we&rsquo;ve come to think of as &ldquo;computer.&rdquo;
That&rsquo;s a good thing - for its market.
I&rsquo;m gratified that Gemmell is on the same page that I am: Apple isn&rsquo;t competing with most of the people we think it&rsquo;s competing with.</p>

<p>The thing to notice here is the difference between Computer Professionals and users.
We IT people get hung up on computers because we like them - and we make them an end in themselves.
That&rsquo;s great for us in our professional roles, but we can&rsquo;t lose sight of the fact that we&rsquo;re abnormal in that regard.
For most people, the computer is just a means to an end, and it&rsquo;s a finicky, mysterious, frustrating means.
Many of the things that Computer Professionals complain about regarding the iPad just <em>do not matter</em> to the actual users that the iPad is targeting.</p>

<p>This is in contrast to the other example I want to talk about, <a href="http://counternotions.com/2010/02/12/buzz/">Google Buzz</a>.
I&rsquo;ll talk about that on Wednesday, and then on Friday talk about the <a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/facebook_wants_to_be_your_one_true_login.php">Facebook/ReadWriteWeb</a> deal.
All of these tie into this theme of perception differences - and I think that all of them point to how we IT people can better be part of the interface between humans and technology.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tablet Signal, Tablet Noise]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/tablet-signal-tablet-noise/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-03T06:01:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/tablet-signal-tablet-noise</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so we&rsquo;re all clear on the fact that Apple has a new device coming out.
It&rsquo;s the iPad, it&rsquo;s going to Change The World.
Great.
Apple&rsquo;s best marketing asset, I believe, is their ability to get all of us talking about their stuff.
It&rsquo;s a pretty pure example of the &ldquo;there&rsquo;s no such thing as bad publicity&rdquo; philosophy: whether we&rsquo;re damning Apple or praising them, we&rsquo;re still talking about them, thinking about them, giving them uncountable dollars of free marketing.
Pulling that off, not just once but repeatedly, is impressive.</p>

<p>Of <em>course</em> I have an opinion about the iPad.
Last month&rsquo;s hyper-excitement has died down a little, but we&rsquo;re all still talking about the dang thing.
I see two important things about the iPad.</p>

<p><strong>Apple got into the processor business</strong>: this is pretty fascinating to me.
If there&rsquo;s a word for Apple under the hand of Jobs, it&rsquo;s &ldquo;gutsy,&rdquo; and deciding to compete with Intel, Motorola and ARM is definitely bold.
Intel, for all that it&rsquo;s not backing the Atom very well, is still in the portable-device-CPU market, and Motorola and ARM are heavily invested in mobile.
Jobs directly positioned Apple as a player in mobile with actions in the past few years, and directly in his iPad announcement speech, so the A4 has to be seen as competing at least a little with the established players.
Of course, they&rsquo;re probably prone to thinking that Apple wants to Take Over The Market.
I&rsquo;m pretty sure that they want no such thing.
As with desktops and Macbooks, Apple wants to be the perfect salesman, selling only to those who are going to buy and leaving the scraps for others.
Apple doesn&rsquo;t want to please everyone - not the way that Google pleases everyone, and certainly not the way that Microsoft tries to please everyone.</p>

<p>Apple wants to please Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.
You&rsquo;ll notice that they&rsquo;ve been pretty damn good at that.
That we can all tell you about the stereotypical Mac user is an interesting feat of marketing.
True or not, Apple has narrative mojo all over the place - and that mojo is focused on attaining 100% market share among Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.
They&rsquo;re doing pretty well at that.
The iPad isn&rsquo;t very bold if you look at it that way: it embodies the proposition that perhaps there are a few people out there that are Apple&rsquo;s kind of people and who haven&rsquo;t bought into the Apple ecosystem at all yet, and who would do so if they got a tablet.
Thus, a tablet.
Otherwise, Apple is not hugely concerned with selling themselves to people who don&rsquo;t <em>want</em> to be Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.
Apple&rsquo;s doing pretty well at the game of not losing customers - I&rsquo;ve never seen them release a product that made people <em>who were already in the Apple Lifestyle</em> say &ldquo;well that&rsquo;s it I&rsquo;m never using another Apple product again!&rdquo;  People do leave the Applesphere, but that&rsquo;s not what pushes them out.</p>

<p>So here sits Apple, with a track record of fairly canny moves and good design, plus a pretty damn good marketing machine, plus a reputation that most Fortune 500 companies would kill for.
Kevin Roberts calls this a &ldquo;lovemark,&rdquo; which I&rsquo;d paraphrase as the kind of product that not only makes people fall in love with it, make it part of their lives, but which also makes them want to evangelize.
And if there&rsquo;s a defining characteristic of the Mac user stereotype, it&rsquo;s that the Mac user is perfectly willing to tell you how great Macs are.
At length.
And Apple&rsquo;s narrative-fu is so strong that despite the massive difference in market cap and bankroll between them and Redmond, they&rsquo;ve managed to define the PC user stereotype as someone who complains about their frequently-broken Windows machine.</p>

<p>Thus, Apple enters the processor business for about the same reason that it does anything else: to make gobsmacking amounts of money by selling Apple products to Apple&rsquo;s kind of people, and slowly, strategically, with risk aversion that would make a casino owner proud, grow the number of Apple&rsquo;s kind of people in the world.
This is part of why, as someone who investigates the connection between narrative, humans, and computers, I am awed by Apple.
For all the many legitimate complaints about Apple the company, the products of Apple the company, and Steve Jobs the person, Apple is just <em>damn</em> good at this business of producing stories that people want to become part of.
Apple is so damn slick.
They are essentially a high-octane design and marketing firm that just happens to sell computers.
Jobs is not kidding when he says that Apple is selling a lifestyle, as he used to when &ldquo;multimedia&rdquo; was a buzzword.
Apple continues to kick ass where it counts because they have defined victory conditions for themselves that are both different from and more attainable than the goals of other companies, and because they are spectacularly good at narrative.
It suffuses what they do.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try it this way.
When Justin Long stands in front of that plain white background and says &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a Mac,&rdquo; and John Hodgman cheerily follows up with &ldquo;And I&rsquo;m a PC,&rdquo; Apple is nakedly making narrative.
For the longest time there just was no serious competition with them.
Even when Microsoft replied, they used Apple&rsquo;s narrative - <em>a narrative within which it was impossible for them to win</em>.
Still, you might actually have a significant mental image now when someone says &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a Windows user.&rdquo;
Microsoft&rsquo;s marketing department has gotten that far.
But &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a Dell user&rdquo;?
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m an Asus user&rdquo;?
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m an HP user&rdquo;?
No, no, no.
Utter blanks as far as personification.
You may have some images of the products' identity, especially if you&rsquo;re part of the enthusiast market.
But I guarantee you that only people who are already neck-deep in caring about computers can call to mind a mental image of &ldquo;Dell user,&rdquo; &ldquo;Asus user,&rdquo; or &ldquo;HP user&rdquo; that&rsquo;s <em>remotely</em> near as clear as those archetypes that Apple is defining through Long and Hodgman.</p>

<p>With the tablet, Apple has made another Apple product which they will sell to Apple&rsquo;s kind of people and make another incremental gain in the definition of &ldquo;Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.&rdquo;
Apple, Apple, Apple.
Seriously, they are playing a whole different game than the rest of the industry.
They are currently set to win, by the way - to win by <em>their</em> definition, which might not look the way you expect it to, and people who think that they&rsquo;re competing with Apple are going to feel like they&rsquo;re losing quite often because they&rsquo;ll do what they think will cause them to win and Apple to lose - and it will slide right off of Apple because they&rsquo;re playing a different game.
And those people will think that Apple is beating them, when it&rsquo;s not doing that either.
For example, people who think that Apple wants to put its OS everywhere are going to go make deals with OEMs to put their OS, not Apple&rsquo;s, on desktops and laptops and phones.
And those people are going to be puzzled when having a tiny slice of market share doesn&rsquo;t make Apple shrivel up and die - because Apple&rsquo;s market share is robust and healthy among the people that Apple cares about selling to.
It goes the same way in other businesses.</p>

<p>This actually brings us to the other thing that I care about with the iPad: <strong>Apple is using its applications as a powerful asset</strong>.
For one, it&rsquo;s a pretty great coup that already the applications - 90% of what people care about with the iPhone and iPod Touch - virtually all run on the iPad.
They&rsquo;re exploiting the success of the iPhone quite well there.
Every single &ldquo;there&rsquo;s an app for that&rdquo; ad that they&rsquo;ve run in the past years just got a tiny bit more valuable, because all those apps will work on the iPad as well as the other two devices.
That&rsquo;s a pretty deft move.
They also made sure that you can transfer apps you&rsquo;ve already bought from your iPod/iPhone to your iPad.
Considerate of them.</p>

<p>The thing with the applications is that it brings up Apple&rsquo;s sinister side.
As <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5458690/">Adam Pash points out</a>, Apple is still holding onto the walled-garden model of app development.
I see a slightly different tradeoff involved here.
For anyone in the consumer mindset, it is entirely irrelevant that Apple harshes on developers - as long as they can find an app that does what they need.
That conditional clause is critical, though.
The people who <em>do</em> care that the App Store is broken - and for them it is, badly - are developers.
No developers, no apps; no apps, no compelling reasons to get an iPad.
We love to mock that speech, but Ballmer was deadly serious when he was up on that stage chanting &ldquo;Developers, developers, developers, developers, developers.&rdquo;
For all the narrative work Apple&rsquo;s done, there still must be things you can do with their products that are worth your time to do.
Hence, apps - and hence why Apple has stayed in the first-party app business tenaciously, producing Safari, Mail, iTunes, iPhoto, and a hundred other basics that come bundled with a Mac.
They&rsquo;re making sure that there&rsquo;s something to <em>do</em> once you&rsquo;re in the Applesphere immediately, and something that doesn&rsquo;t require you to wade through the endless crapware installed with most Windows machines purchased at retail.</p>

<p>Part of why Apple gets away with being so controlling and jerkish about apps for the iPhone OS is that thing about selling to Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.
Apple has a pretty good read on what Apple&rsquo;s kind of people want - and that means that imposing those restrictions, when they&rsquo;re right, isn&rsquo;t that big a deal.
Apple&rsquo;s spin is that they&rsquo;re restricting developers to what developers would end up doing anyhow: catering to Apple users.
But developers themselves are not at all guaranteed to be Apple&rsquo;s kind of people: developers may come to Apple for entirely different reasons.
Anyone who uses an Apple product because of its Unix guts, for example, stands a pretty good chance of not actually being Apple&rsquo;s kind of people.
Apple&rsquo;s kind of people, I would say, have better things to do with their time than tinker with a computer - they want to be doing a task.
Watching their movie, looking at their web sites, showing off their photos.
Apple happily enables those tasks.</p>

<p>Developers, on the other hand, want to look under the hood, poke around, and adjust things.
They want to bend the computer to their personal idiom of what a computer should do.
This is why they develop software: they want to impose their will on the computer (although usually it&rsquo;s much, much less Nietzschean than that and more like &ldquo;I want a Twitter client that doesn&rsquo;t suck&rdquo; or &ldquo;I need to provide clever services to the real estate agents that work for my company&rdquo; or &ldquo;I wonder what happens if I write a database that works in a different way&rdquo;).
Apple has already imposed a ton of will on that computer, and so Apple has baked in a certain amount of resistance to developers.</p>

<p>They know that they need developers, and they actively court developers - but one of the flaws of the Apple way of doing things is that it can&rsquo;t avoid a certain degree of hostility to developers.
Developers care about things that Apple&rsquo;s customers don&rsquo;t (even when developers buy MacBooks and iPhones and, inevitably, iPads).
Fortunately, Apple can give developers most of what they want without having to upset the average iPhone buyer - but they&rsquo;re reluctant to go too far with that, because the more ground they give to the developers, the harder it&rsquo;ll be to keep control of the Apple narrative.
They are damn right to be reluctant, to my mind: the Apple narrative is their biggest corporate asset.</p>

<p>Thus, Apple balances those concerns: trying to make their customers happy and trying to make their developers happy.
Apple is good enough at the former that if that&rsquo;s all they had to do, I would expect them to keep incrementally growing until they own the planet.
But making developers happy is something that Apple is merely average at - and that, I think, represents a genuine risk to them.
Not a risk that&rsquo;ll make them go out of business in the next quarter, the next year, even the next decade.
I would say that Apple&rsquo;s huge narrative power is so much of a boost that it lets them mostly ignore the developer issue.
However, if the narrative power vanishes - and it&rsquo;ll certainly take a big, big hit when Jobs inevitably kicks the bucket - Apple will have to be prepared to deal with its game from less of a position of strength.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;ll be worth watching, once it happens - and that&rsquo;ll leave open a space for someone with another really kick-ass narrative and a great design team to step up and become the company that befuddles the rest of its industry with the way it just doesn&rsquo;t lose, even when it really should, because it&rsquo;s playing a different game and telling a different story.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
