<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: craigslist | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/craigslist/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2016-07-20T19:23:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Politicos' Problematic Incentives Harm Craigslist]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/politicos-problematic-incentives-harm-craigslist/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-31T23:01:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/politicos-problematic-incentives-harm-craigslist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So there&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2010/08/29/BUGI1F4F9K.DTL">even more noise</a> about suing Craigslist,
and I wish I could grab the attorneys general of 18 states by one giant pair of pinstriped lapels and shout &ldquo;You are making this problem <strong>WORSE</strong>, you buncha maroons!&rdquo;
There&rsquo;s still some space to write about this after <a href="http://stronglyemergent.com/blog/2010/the-many-forms-of-not-getting-it/">last time</a>, and I&rsquo;m gonna go ahead and fill that space.</p>

<p>The problem here is a toxic incentive structure, just like <a href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/02/cya_security_1.html">the reason the TSA reduces security</a>.
The various political folk who are inveighing against Craigslist have no idea what they&rsquo;re talking about and are going to make Craigslist less useful for everyone and cost their taxpayers a lot of money in the process - and yet, for them personally, there is no downside to attacking Craigslist.
Attacking Craigslist makes them look &ldquo;tough on crime,&rdquo; look like vigorous, active advocates of the public good, and look like paragons of conventional morality.</p>

<p>The most effective things you can do to increase airline security and reduce sex trafficking are the most boring ones, and the current structure of incentives all but guarantees that those measures will not be taken, and instead countermeasures will be taken that will make the problem worse.
This underscores again the importance of narrative.
Software providers and other technical people are in danger because of these toxic incentives - people who don&rsquo;t know how your business works could have an incentive to mess with you, and are quite likely to be immune to consequences in the practical sense.
This is why we developers and sysadmins need to be aware of the social, political, and cultural context of our professional actions - the less aware we are, the more likely that we&rsquo;ll find ourselves out of a job, at the helm of a foundering company, or forced to implement asinine requirements because of forces beyond our control.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Many Forms Of Not Getting It]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/the-many-forms-of-not-getting-it/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-10T23:01:22-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/the-many-forms-of-not-getting-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craigslist_controversies_and_illegal_activities_by_users">suing Craigslist</a> again, and again I have to hide my face in my hands.
Suing Craigslist because people post problematic material there is like the kids in <em>Scream</em> suing AT&amp;T because the killer used a telephone.</p>

<p>I have to wonder what the plaintiffs' thought process is, considering how long Craigslist has been working on foiling the people who try to cheat its system in a variety of ways.
A <a href="http://www.wired.com/entertainment/theweb/magazine/17-09/ff_craigslist?currentPage=all">Wired article from this time last year</a> is a far more educational look at the matter.
Craigslist is an astonishing <em>rara avis</em> in the business world - not just a company with a commitment to not being evil that makes Google look like pikers, but with a business model that gives them a proper interest in being good stewards of their classified-ad content.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t yet seen an accusation against Craigslist that seemed to be remotely grounded in fact - they&rsquo;re a great example of how successful Silicon Valley businesses seem to be lightning rods for nuisance lawsuits.
Generally libertarianism is for prats, but I can&rsquo;t blame startup folks for finding it appealing in the face of an appalling level of Not Getting It from the establishment business world and certain segments of the general public.
No-one likes being beholden to fools.</p>

<p>That said, you have to keep in mind that generally power makes fools out of people.
This is part of why I respect Craigslist: they&rsquo;ve taken big steps to avoid becoming idiots with power.
The difference between them and the established business world is sharp.
Look at <a href="http://www.lettersofnote.com/2010/08/tiger-oil-memos.html">these memoranda from a 1970s executive</a>, for example - anyone who&rsquo;s worked in the business world probably recognizes that that attitude hasn&rsquo;t gone away at all.</p>

<p>Those memoranda lead to another point, too: people are rarely as foolish as they are when they&rsquo;re seeking complete control over others.
Complete control over pretty much anything, especially other people, is a chimera, and in pursuing it, you will only harm yourself and others.
Craigslist accepts that there are limits to that control, and in that acceptance, show that they&rsquo;re smarter than pretty much anyone suing them.</p>

<p>Lawsuits actually make another good example of this: what is a suit but an attempt to control - change - another&rsquo;s behavior?
Yet part of the reason lawsuits are so difficult is that rarely do the plaintiffs understand what produced the behavior they seek to change.
It&rsquo;s not an easy task - usually the defendants don&rsquo;t understand what they&rsquo;re doing either, they just understand that someone is trying to <em>make</em> them change, and so they resist coercion with all their might, no matter whether the change is good for them or not.
A cease-and-desist letter can quite reliably turn respectable businesspeople into petulant children screaming the adult equivalent of &ldquo;<em>you can&rsquo;t MAKE me do anything!</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>So pursuing control with a blunt instrument like a lawsuit is inefficient - and so is using a blunt instrument like a law or a word-filtering software utility.
What do we have that can do the job? Human social constructs and cultural constructs - and it&rsquo;s not a coincidence that part of why Craigslist works well is that it has welcomed those as ways to control its community, and accepted that it can&rsquo;t completely control the social and cultural norms around its site.
Craigslist has cultivated a community, invested in creating a trustworthy community, and is reaping its just rewards for a long-term investment in human decency.</p>

<p>The lesson here for sysadmins and developers is this: programmatic limits on human behavior have harsh diminishing-returns curves.
You need to know when it&rsquo;s not worth your effort to implement more programmatic control, and at that point turn to social and cultural measures.
Social and cultural measures remove some control from the owners of a system, but can reward them with a better system.
You also need to know whether you want to work for someone who insists on chasing complete control of a system they own - they may not all be as bad as the &lsquo;70s executive, but they&rsquo;re definitely out there.
I hope that when you and I find them, we have enough control over our own lives to walk away instead of uselessly burning resources trying to control the uncontrollable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
