<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dreamweaver | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/dreamweaver/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2016-07-20T17:18:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Bother With Dreamweaver]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/dont-bother-with-dreamweaver/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-17T22:01:36-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/dont-bother-with-dreamweaver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This, like the Flash post, is an angry post.
Also like Flash, I have a class that consists basically of &ldquo;learn to use this Adobe product.&rdquo;  That&rsquo;s not inherently bad, but it has some problems - especially when you combine it with a textbook that is also a sales brochure for the thing that it&rsquo;s teaching you to use.
I think that that&rsquo;s unethical and usually a sign of a cruddy textbook.</p>

<p>Dreamweaver, like Flash, is basically past its sell-by date.
Its feature-set is best for the low-end, but as a member of Adobe&rsquo;s Creative Suite of apps, it&rsquo;s priced for the high end.
If you&rsquo;re just tinkering with web sites, with static pages, it might be helpful - but it&rsquo;s also quite likely to be overwhelming.
If you&rsquo;re on the high end, writing web content in PHP/Ruby/Python, Dreamweaver is probably going to be inadequate, especially if you&rsquo;ve already got your own IDE and content management.
I can&rsquo;t see a good spot in the market for it.
I&rsquo;ll grant that it would have been an amazing tool to have in 1999, and to Macromedia&rsquo;s credit, it <em>was</em> pretty dang good in 1999.
But it hasn&rsquo;t been 1999 for a long time now.</p>

<p>Modern web content creation has simply outgrown Dreamweaver.
This is less speculative than with Flash - Dreamweaver is straight-up inadequate, and its presence in business environments is a sign of clinging to legacy commitments that are long-term losers.
Anything Dreamweaver can do can probably be accomplished for free with fewer licensing headaches and a lower workstation and server resource footprint.</p>

<p>Despite the kvetching about Dreamweaver and Flash, I&rsquo;m pretty fond of Adobe.
Dreamweaver and Flash both <em>had</em> a useful lifetime, which is more than you can say for some products, and as corporations go, Adobe is fairly non-evil.
But right now, it looks like <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001296.html">any application that <em>can</em> be written in JavaScript, <em>will</em> eventually be written in JavaScript.</a> This is trouble for Adobe, one of the giants of desktop software, a company with a lot to lose by anyone&rsquo;s measure.
They&rsquo;ve responded with Adobe Air, which is nice, but seems unlikely to replace browsers for the tasks that Adobe&rsquo;s core apps address.
What else is Adobe doing to move to the next paradigm?
I hope it&rsquo;s doing something, because we&rsquo;re seeing irrefutable evidence in the music, movie, and dead-tree industries that trying to sue the next paradigm out of existence is a loser&rsquo;s game and just ensures that you won&rsquo;t make money on what comes next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
