<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T21:47:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Past Is A Foreign Country]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2013/the-past-is-a-foreign-country/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-02T16:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2013/the-past-is-a-foreign-country</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Communicating with your past self can be a little alarming.
In the process of converting this blog to OctoPress
(because <a href="http://me.veekun.com/blog/2012/04/09/php-a-fractal-of-bad-design/">PHP is a fractal of bad design</a> and WordPress has its own problems on top of being a huge PHP legacy system),
I learned not only that <code>Liquid Exception: Unknown tag 'endif' in page</code> is Liquid&rsquo;s way of saying &ldquo;you forgot to <em>start</em> that if-block, girl&rdquo;, I learned that my past self had very different priorities.</p>

<p>Not that this is <a href="news:">news:</a> as I&rsquo;ve gotten older, I&rsquo;ve gotten better at forgiving my past self for her fuckups.
It&rsquo;s still hard to forgive her eating habits, but bodies are complicated.
I was surprised, though, to learn that she was conflicted about whether to be a developer or a sysadmin.
Seriously?
It&rsquo;s not a binary: pretty much the whole subfield of devops is people who&rsquo;re making interesting choices about &ldquo;what if I pick things from both skillsets?&rdquo;
While I now think of myself as an engineer in general, not a sysadin or a developer, I am very happy that I am picking up bits and pieces of CS theory and that I can still read Apache config files, whip up basic Perl one-liners, and be on speaking terms with <code>vim</code>.</p>

<p>I admire the dedicated systems team at my work, but their job is not the job I want to do.
I want to <em>build things.</em>
That&rsquo;s gotten more and more important to me over time &mdash; the thrill of green-field development, of Something from Nothing, is one I want, over and over.
Lucky me: I am getting better and better at producing that experience for myself and making useful things along the way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
