<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T21:47:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sherlock Holmes, Search Engine Optimizer]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-03T06:01:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/sherlock-holmes-search-engine-optimizer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A culture of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honour">honor</a> is a remarkably convenient thing for a writer.
A writer needs characters to do stupid things on a regular basis, and nothing so dependably produces idiotic behavior as a character bound by honor.
Importantly, it produces a very credible kind of idiocy:
let a character clench his hand against his chest, grit his teeth, glower, and declare that he <em>must</em> undertake some course of action for his sacred honor&mdash;
and other characters will easily nod along and agree, and readers who either live in or are passingly familiar with a culture of honor (which is nearly all of them) will understand what is going on without thinking, merely by this incident, that your character is a moron not worth reading about.</p>

<p>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle used this device frequently, and to good effect.
I recently re-read the Sherlock Holmes canon over the course of a few days, and matters of honor frequently cropped up.
I noticed, too, that Holmes, conveniently, was always on the side of honor.
There is of course a large body of Holmes scholarship, both more and <a href="http://www.tor.com/blogs/2009/02/on-the-fannish-phenomenon-of-sherlock-holmes-or-my-fandom-is-crazier-than-your-fandom">less lucid</a>, but I only propose to extend it, not to contradict it.</p>

<p>I noticed that honor, in the Sherlock Holmes canon, leads Holmes to a very effective method of search engine optimization.
The newspapers and the telegraph were impressive advances, and changed the information environment of the 19th century enormously, but personal reputation was, then as now, a tremendously important source of information about others.
Holmes consistently trades away recognition in mass media in favor of gaining personal reputation as a man of honor and discretion.
He optimizes his reputation for a specific audience:
the wealthy of England.
There are many cases that he takes on for no money at all, which serve (in addition to their stated purpose) to build a reputation for him as a man of sterling moral character.
We see his reward for this over the course of the stories:
the nobility and royalty of Europe resort to him, and reward him handsomely.</p>

<p>Holmes eschews joining the official police or intelligence forces; he is an entrepreneur.
He aims for a very specific market, and achieves his aims.
He has the dual aims of sustaining his appetite for interesting problems, and of sustaining his appetite for a roof over his head, good food, and supplies for his various studies.
This isn&rsquo;t the most obvious layer of the stories - but quickly becomes apparent on a careful reading.
Sherlock Holmes is not just a great detective, he is a very proficient marketer.
He knows where his services fetch the best price, markets there, and throws the rest to the winds.
This is only obscured by the fact that there are two prices that may be paid for Sherlock Holmes' involvement, and the more important one is that the problem be interesting.
It takes - as in &ldquo;The Adventure of the Priory School&rdquo; - quite a tremendous amount of money to awaken anything like avarice in Holmes.
Still it cannot be doubted, from the notes that his biographer gives us, that he is very efficient at making a comfortable living from himself.</p>

<p>The lesson we can draw from Sherlock Holmes is basically one about optimization.
Figure out what&rsquo;s important to you, and optimize towards that - even if it looks strange to other people.
Holmes has a way to achieve both money and a steady supply of interesting problems&mdash;
and troubles himself with nothing else, to the perennial puzzlement of Lestrade and the rest of the police forces.
Go and do likewise: build a reputation where it matters for getting what you want, and pay the rest no mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Textbook Economics]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/textbook-economics/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-20T06:01:23+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/textbook-economics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve come across an interesting dynamic with my textbooks.
I tend to pick up a couple of new ones every six weeks or so because of my school schedule.
They&rsquo;re necessary for a relatively short time, which means that I don&rsquo;t have much inertia when a &ldquo;do I get rid of this?&rdquo; decision comes up.
I have a very strong inertia for books - I hate getting rid of things in general, I have a distinct case of &ldquo;but I might use that!&rdquo; and that means that I have a hard time getting rid of books normally.</p>

<p>The textbooks, however, get around this.
I don&rsquo;t own them for long enough that inertia overrides other factors, and while I do develop an emotional relationship with them, it&rsquo;s antagonistic sometimes, so that&rsquo;s a wash.
Importantly, there&rsquo;s also a decision point every six weeks or so where I can get actual money for the books.
So I get to ask myself - will this book be valuable enough as a reference work that I want to forgo getting money for it?  Judging my textbooks by that standard has been interesting.</p>

<ul>
<li>CompTIA A+ Guide To Managing &amp; Maintaining Your PC, 6th Edition: A half-assed textbook, and makes a terrible, terrible reference book.
I&rsquo;d have sold it if I could, and right now I&rsquo;m trying to figure out a way to give it away constructively.</li>
<li>70-270: Installing, Configuring, and Administering Microsoft Windows XP Professional: Hideously dated despite XP sticking around, would sell it if I could, but no such luck.
Same for the accompanying exercise book.
Microsoft Press is not endearing its products to me, and I bet I&rsquo;ll have to deal with more of them in the future.</li>
<li>MS Office Textbook, title not recalled: Absolute junk, got rid of it as soon as possible, a gratuitously bad reference work and for my frame of mind an even worse textbook.</li>
<li>CompTIA Net+ Study Guide: Has significant flaws - its security chapters are long on &ldquo;woooo, evil hackers!&rdquo; and on goofy names for attacks - but overall it&rsquo;s worth keeping for reference.
Author attempts to be hip and with it, very mixed results, but at least doesn&rsquo;t sound like the soulless corporate drone who wrote the A+ Guide.</li>
<li>Lynda.com Dreamweaver CS3 Hands-On Training: Thoroughly mediocre, has a fawning, sales-brochure tone about the product.
The class is inspiring a hearty contempt for Dreamweaver, as recently seen on this blog, so there&rsquo;s no way I&rsquo;m keeping this one.</li>
<li>Adobe Classroom In A Book Flash CS3 Professional: Also crap, also a sales brochure for the product (although I expect it a little more, similar to what I expect from Microsoft Press).
Mildly more worth as a reference work and mildly better software, still not keeping it.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to classes like I took in my first attempt at college, where it was a lecturer and an O'Reilly book or two.
O'Reilly books, whether meant as textbooks or not, generally retain a lot of value as reference works - it&rsquo;s pretty much universal across computer folk that they&rsquo;ll have O'Reilly books sitting around.
Most of them have better typography and design than the glossy textbooks I&rsquo;ve been using, too.</p>

<p>This ties into a general crankiness of mine about shiny things.
I mistrust them.
Past a very low threshhold, it&rsquo;s <em>hard</em> to make additional dollars spent on thick pages, color printing, and big pictures pay off in better information absorption/retention rates.
More commonly, extra money spent on prettying things up will have no effect on those rates, and be wasted - be spent on things besides rigorous <em>content</em>.
I feel like money misspent in that direction is money spent to deceive me, and money that results in higher prices because it adds features that I don&rsquo;t value.
I want <em>content</em>.
As a result, I like the O'Reilly books because they put aside the temptation to be shiny and deliver excellent content, reliably.</p>

<p>This is also the reason why I want this web site to get more spare and lean in the future.
I want it to be a web site that I&rsquo;d want to read.
There is a place for bright color and CSS tricks and busy graphics.
That place is not on a page where the primary content is straight text.
When straight text is the content, everything else is a distraction.
I aspire to the Tuftean ideal where communicating data well is the entire task of the page - no wasted &ldquo;ink&rdquo; at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
