<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T21:47:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Innovative Business Model]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2013/an-innovative-business-model/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-05T20:57:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2013/an-innovative-business-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every so often Pantone blows my mind.
Their business model is that they <em>sell colors</em>&mdash;not that they sell paint or ink or dye, no, they sell <em>colors!</em>
It&rsquo;s a little unbelievable.
Of course if you venture into the world of printing, publishing, and large-scale content creation in general,
color is just one of many important details that have to not only be right, but right in a way that you can talk to others sensibly about.
So Pantone can be thought of as a standards body like ISO&mdash;
and like ISO, they aren&rsquo;t cheap, and they look rather surreal from the outside.</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re a great lesson in that way, though:
sometimes to understand odd things, you have to meet them on their own terms, not on yours.
Otherwise you&rsquo;ll be looking at <a href="http://www.pantone.com/pages/index.aspx?pg=21055">&ldquo;Emerald is the color of the year!&rdquo;</a> and be staring at your monitor mouthing
&ldquo;what the devil does that mean, who decided that, how the heck is a color &lsquo;lush&rsquo;?&rdquo;
But it makes perfect sense on its own terms.
Like many other things in the world, it exists for itself and those who know it, not for strangers.</p>

<p>Of course, you may want to treat my opinion on the matter with skepticism
since I&rsquo;m the kind of person who finds the <a href="http://www.pantone.com/pages/products/product.aspx?pid=1376&amp;ca=33">Emerald Pantone iPhone Case</a> mildly fetching.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
