<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pylons | Strongly Emergent]]></title>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/categories/pylons/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-10-30T20:37:03-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Strongly Emergent Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pylons Field Scheduler: Planning]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/pylons-field-scheduler-planning/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-15T06:01:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/pylons-field-scheduler-planning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;d been leaning on the digital version of <a href="http://pylonsbook.com">The Definitive Guide to Pylons</a>, but I was gifted <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1590599349?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stronemerg-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1590599349">the physical version</a> not too long ago.
I&rsquo;m jazzed about that: having another form for that data is going to be useful for me.
With that in hand, I&rsquo;m starting on another Pylons project.
This may evolve into my project for the Pylons course that I&rsquo;m trying to get my school to approve, but I&rsquo;m going to do it even if I don&rsquo;t get the class approved, because it&rsquo;s interesting and if I do it well it&rsquo;ll be useful to someone I care about.</p>

<p>This is a trivial project overall, but that&rsquo;s what you do as part of the learning curve.
This project will create a web site for scheduling the use of sports fields.
Users will be able to visit the site and easily see what&rsquo;s currently scheduled and create requests for field usage.
Fields will show up as available at a given time, booked, or request-pending.
Requests go to field coordinators, who resolve conflicts and approve requests for field usage.
They should be able to do this as quickly as possible - current mechanism envisions that field requests generate an email to the coordinator or coordinators, who can click on a generated link in the URL and approve the request just by that click.
Non-response is the same as declining approval.
So the coordinators have a bit of a workload, but that&rsquo;s what it means to be a coordinator anyhow.</p>

<p>Expect more posts to show up with notes towards this project.
I&rsquo;ve got a catchy name for it, too.
&ldquo;Field Availability and Scheduling Tool.&rdquo;
FAST - that&rsquo;s a good acronym, not worsened by the number of projects that have already used it.</p>

<p>What I&rsquo;ll be trying to consciously think of during this project is data structures.
What do I need to provide?
What kind of database structure is best for sitting under this, even if I&rsquo;m only going to interact with it through SQLAlchemy?
How can I keep the system open to further use with minimal overhead?</p>

<p>My ambition - we&rsquo;ll see if I can actually pull it off - is to follow this up with an app that creates a schedule for students and teachers given a set of constraints (working on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_satisfiability_problem">3SAT problems</a>, basically, and trying to figure out what the difficulty class of this one is).
After that, I&rsquo;d like to write a recommendation engine.
Neither of these are trivial projects, and there&rsquo;s a pretty good chance that I won&rsquo;t get them done before graduation.
That&rsquo;s okay.
The journey is the important thing; and if I make it through the journey to get them working (nevermind working at a high level of optimization), I&rsquo;ll be willing to call myself pretty handy with Python.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proposed Course: Pylons]]></title>
    <link href="http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/proposed-course-pylons/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-29T06:01:57+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://stronglyemergent.com//blog/2010/proposed-course-pylons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Of course, after spending most of 400 words complaining in my last post, an obvious question comes up: <em>well, what are you going to do about it?</em>
What I&rsquo;m doing about it is writing up a course - and more than one, if I get a positive reception - that will let me create the hybrid curriculum I want, and pitching it to the school&rsquo;s administration.
I&rsquo;ve used Google Docs to <a href="http://docs.google.com/View?id=ddvszwtj_44hpttscd3">write up a course proposal</a> (which is going to keep being updated, it&rsquo;s very much work-in-progress) for the first thing I have in mind.</p>

<p>What I have in mind is using <a href="http://pylonshq.com">Pylons</a>.
Pylons is an open-source web framework built on Python.
I&rsquo;ve been working on Python gradually on my own time, but I&rsquo;m not happy with my progress.
I haven&rsquo;t been making progress because I haven&rsquo;t been putting in enough time.
Therefore, I want to create a school project in which I have to use Pylons because that will require me to put in more time on it, and give me a structure for using my time.
That&rsquo;s pretty much the most useful thing that I get from school: I could get most of the information from pure reference works freely available (appearances to the contrary, it&rsquo;s not like Microsoft or Red Hat <em>want</em> to keep people from knowing how to run their servers well), but school gives it structure and enacts a framework for practice.
Practice - that Gladwellian 10,000 hours - is essential.
So when I have a structure for my time, it&rsquo;s easier to put in the purposeful practice required to achieve proficiency (and after that, mastery).</p>

<p>Fortunately, this project of creating a Pylons class has an excellent fallback position.
Even if I don&rsquo;t persuade the school to let me take my course - and it&rsquo;s definitely not a sure thing - I can use that framework to structure my own time and make more progress.
So I&rsquo;m happy about that.
I wouldn&rsquo;t design the course if I had already done all of the work - as it is, I&rsquo;m designing the course around what I need to learn, and it&rsquo;s an interesting challenge to develop a plan for learning things that I don&rsquo;t yet know.
I definitely think that my path will be easier if I can save the school&rsquo;s administration as much work as possible.
I want to plop down a sheaf of paper for them and say - &ldquo;here is <em>the whole course</em>, how about letting me do it?&rdquo;
I will give them a syllabus, quizzes and answer keys, homework assignments, a textbook, and a letter of recommendation from someone saying &ldquo;yeah these are marketable skills.&rdquo;
I hope that they&rsquo;ll find that persuasive.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s another reason to craft this course, though, that I should have covered in the last post.
I hope that it will replace some courses here that <em>suck</em>.
Unless you&rsquo;re getting into serious mojo and/or VBA, Word and Excel are not suitable subjects for technical college classes.
Learning to use them up to a basic, everyday level is a long afternoon&rsquo;s work.
The curriculum here feels padded with classes like that, that have no place in seriously preparing for a job in the IT world.
I&rsquo;m familiar with and sympathetic to the argument that peripheral skills are near in importance to technical skills, and that preparation for the professional world should be holistic, but come on.
I feel like my tuition is not well spent when it is spent on content-free classes.
So as far as I possibly can, I&rsquo;m going to roll my own education, I&rsquo;m going to pitch classes at the Administration that are <em>not</em> content-free, and use them to replace content-free classes.</p>

<p>Setting a goal and working with a bureaucratic institution to get it, crafting a proposal, negotiating, accepting a higher work-load in order to have more gratifying work?  <em>Those</em> are career skills I want.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
